<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "docbook-dtd-45/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="dependencies">
  <title>Making use of Dependencies</title>

  <para>
    CG-3 can work with dependency trees in various ways. The input cohorts can have existing
    dependencies; the grammar can create new attachments; or a combination of the two.
  </para>

  <section id="dep-setparent">
    <title>SETPARENT</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>SETPARENT</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <screen>
      [wordform] SETPARENT &lt;target&gt; [contextual_tests]
          TO|FROM &lt;contextual_target&gt; [contextual_tests] ;
    </screen>
    <para>
      Attaches the matching reading to the contextually targetted cohort as a child.
      The last link of the contextual test is used as target.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the contextual target is a scanning test and the first found candidate cannot be attached
      due to loop prevention, SETPARENT will look onwards for the next candidate.
      This can be controlled with rule option <link linkend="rule-options-nearest">NEAREST</link>
      and <link linkend="rule-options-allowloop">ALLOWLOOP</link>.
    </para>
    <screen>
      SETPARENT targetset (-1* ("someword"))
      &nbsp; TO (1* (step) LINK 1* (candidate)) (2 SomeSet) ;
    </screen>
  </section>

  <section id="dep-setchild">
    <title>SETCHILD</title>
    <indexterm>
      <primary>SETCHILD</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <screen>
      [wordform] SETCHILD &lt;target&gt; [contextual_tests]
          TO|FROM &lt;contextual_target&gt; [contextual_tests] ;
    </screen>
    <para>
      Attaches the matching reading to the contextually targetted cohort as the parent.
      The last link of the contextual test is used as target.
    </para>
    <para>
      If the contextual target is a scanning test and the first found candidate cannot be attached
      due to loop prevention, SETCHILD will look onwards for the next candidate.
      This can be controlled with rule option <link linkend="rule-options-nearest">NEAREST</link>
      and <link linkend="rule-options-allowloop">ALLOWLOOP</link>.
    </para>
    <screen>
      SETCHILD targetset (-1* ("someword"))
      &nbsp; TO (1* (step) LINK 1* (candidate)) (2 SomeSet) ;
    </screen>
  </section>

  <section id="dep-input">
    <title>Existing Trees in Input</title>
    <para>
      Dependency attachments in input comes in the form of #X-&gt;Y or #X→Y tags where X is the number of the current
      node and Y is the number of the parent node. The X must be unique positive integers and should
      be sequentially enumerated. '0' is reserved and means the root of the tree, so no node may claim
      to be '0', but nodes may attach to '0'.
    </para>
    <para>
      <emphasis>If the Y of a reading cannot be located, it will be reattached to itself.</emphasis>
      <emphasis>If a reading contains more than one attachment, only the last will be honored.</emphasis>
      <emphasis>If a cohort has conflicting attachments in its readings, the result is undefined.</emphasis>
    </para>
    <para>
      For example:
      <screen>
        "&lt;There&gt;"
        &nbsp; "there" &lt;*&gt; ADV @F-SUBJ #1-&gt;0
        "&lt;once&gt;"
        &nbsp; "once" ADV @ADVL #2-&gt;0
        "&lt;was&gt;"
        &nbsp; "be" &lt;SVC/N&gt; &lt;SVC/A&gt; V PAST SG1/3 VFIN IMP @FMV #3-&gt;2
        "&lt;a&gt;"
        &nbsp; "a" &lt;Indef&gt; ART DET CENTRAL SG @&gt;N #4-&gt;5
        "&lt;man&gt;"
        &nbsp; "man" N NOM SG @SC #5-&gt;0
        "&lt;$.&gt;"
      </screen>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="dep-delimit">
    <title>Using Dependency as Delimiters</title>
    <para>
      Cmdline flag -D or --dep-delimit will enable the use of dependency information to delimit windows.
      Enabling this will disable <link linkend="keyword-delimiters">DELIMITERS</link> entirely,
      but will not affect the behavior of <link linkend="keyword-soft-delimiters">SOFT-DELIMITERS</link>
      nor the hard/soft cohort limits.
    </para>
    <para>
      Windows are delimited if a cohort has a node number less than or equal to
      the highest previously seen node number, and also if a cohort has a node number that seems like a discontinuous
      jump up in numbers.
      The discontinuous limit is by default 10 but you can pass a number to -D/--dep-delimit to set it yourself.
      Some systems do not output dependency numbers for punctuation, so setting it too low may break those;
      the default 10 was chosen since it is unlikely any real text would have 10 sequential cohorts not part of the tree.
    </para>
    <para>
      For example:
      <emphasis>#4→5 followed by #3→4 will delimit.</emphasis>
      <emphasis>#4→5 followed by #4→4 will delimit.</emphasis>
      <emphasis>#4→5 followed by #15→4 will delimit.</emphasis>
      <emphasis>#4→5 followed by #5→3 will not delimit.</emphasis>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="dep-grammar">
    <title>Creating Trees from Grammar</title>
    <para>
      It is also possible to create or modify the tree on-the-fly with rules.
      See <link linkend="keyword-setparent">SETPARENT</link>
      and <link linkend="keyword-setchild">SETCHILD</link>.
      Dependencies created in this fashion will be output in the same format as above.
    </para>
    <para>
      For example:
      <screen>
        SETPARENT (@&gt;N) (0 (ART DET))
        &nbsp; TO (1* (N)) ;

        SETPARENT (@&lt;P)
        &nbsp; TO (-1* (PRP)) (NEGATE 1* (V)) ;
      </screen>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="dep-contextual-tests">
    <title>Contextual Tests</title>
    <para>
      Either case, once you have a dependency tree to work with,
      you can use that in subsequent contextual tests as seen below.
      These positions can be combined with the window spanning options.
    </para>

    <section id="dep-ct-parent">
      <title>Parent</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>p</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'p' position asks for the parent of the current position.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (-1* (ADJ) LINK p (N))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-ancestors">
      <title>Ancestors</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>pp</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'pp' position asks for an ancestor of the current position,
        where ancestor is defined as any parent, grand-parent, great-grand-parent, etc...
      </para>
      <screen>
        (-1* (N) LINK pp (ADJ))
      </screen>
      <para>
        <emphasis>The analogue of <link linkend="gotcha-cc-vs-cstar">difference between cc and c*</link> applies to pp vs. p*</emphasis>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-children">
      <title>Children</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>c</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'c' position asks for a child of the current position.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (-1* (N) LINK c (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-descendents">
      <title>Descendents</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>cc</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'cc' position asks for a descendent of the current position,
        where descendent is defined as any child, grand-child, great-grand-child, etc...
      </para>
      <screen>
        (-1* (N) LINK cc (ADJ))
      </screen>
      <para>
        <emphasis><link linkend="gotcha-cc-vs-cstar">Difference between cc and c*</link></emphasis>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-siblings">
      <title>Siblings</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>s</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 's' position asks for a sibling of the current position.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (-1* (ADJ) LINK s (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-self">
      <title>Self</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>S</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'S' option allows the test to look at the current target as well.
        Used in conjunction with p, c, cc, s, or r to test self and the relations.
      </para>
      <para>
        Be aware that BARRIER and CBARRIER will check and thus possibly stop at the current target when 'S' is in effect.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (cS (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-deep">
      <title>Deep Scan</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>*</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The '*' option behaves differently when dealing with dependencies.
        Here, the '*' option allows the test to perform a deep scan.
        Used in conjunction with p, c, or s to continue until there are no deeper relations.
        For example, position 'c*' tests the children, grand-children, great-grand-children, and so forth.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (c* (ADJ))
      </screen>
      <para>
        <emphasis><link linkend="gotcha-cc-vs-cstar">Difference between cc and c*</link></emphasis>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-leftof">
      <title>Left of</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>l</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'l' option limits the search to cohorts that are to the left of the current target.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (lc (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-rightof">
      <title>Right of</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>r</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'r' option limits the search to cohorts that are to the right of the current target.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (rc (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-leftmost">
      <title>Leftmost</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>ll</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>lll</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>llr</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'll' option limits the search to the leftmost cohort of the possible matches.
        Note that this cohort may be to the right of the current target;
        use 'lll' if you want the leftmost of the cohorts to the left of the current target,
        or 'llr' if you want the leftmost of the cohorts to the right of the current target.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (llc (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-rightmost">
      <title>Rightmost</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>rr</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>rrr</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>rrl</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'rr' option limits the search to the rightmost cohort of the possible matches.
        Note that this cohort may be to the left of the current target;
        use 'rrr' if you want the rightmost of the cohorts to the right of the current target,
        or 'rrl' if you want the rightmost of the cohorts to the left of the current target.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (rrc (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-all">
      <title>All Scan</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>ALL</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'ALL' option will require that all of the relations match the set.
        For example, position 'ALL s' requires that all of the siblings match the set.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (ALL s (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>

    <section id="dep-ct-not">
      <title>None Scan</title>
      <indexterm>
        <primary>NONE</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>
        The 'NONE' option will require that none of the relations match the set.
        For example, position 'NONE c' requires that none of the children match the set.
      </para>
      <screen>
        (NONE c (ADJ))
      </screen>
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>
