<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "docbook-dtd-45/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="intro">
  <title>Intro</title>

  <section id="caveat">
    <title>Caveat Emptor</title>
    <para>
      <emphasis>
        This manual should be regarded as a guideline. Some of the features or functionality
        described is either not implemented yet, or does not work exactly as advertised.
        A good place to see what is and is not implemented is to run the regression test suite
        as the test names are indicative of features. The individual tests are also good starting points
        to find examples on how a specific feature works.
      </emphasis>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="whatis">
    <title>What this is...</title>
    <para>
      This document describes the design, features, implementation, usability, etc
      of an evolution in the <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constraint_Grammar">constraint grammar</ulink> formalism.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="naming">
    <title>Naming</title>
    <para>
      I have called this version of CG "VISL CG-3" since it implements the functionality of the
      VISL CG-2 variant of constraint grammar and is a
      general update of the grammar format and parser features that warrants a version bump.
      VISL CG-3 is feature-wise backwards compatible with CG-2 and VISLCG, and contains switches
      to enforce their respective behavior in certain areas.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="unicode">
    <title>Unicode</title>
    <para>
      Even before any other designing and development had started, the desire to include
      <ulink url="http://unicode.org/">Unicode</ulink> support was a strong requirement.
      By default, the codepage for the grammar file, input stream, and output stream is
      detected from the environment.
      Internally and through switches there is full support
      for Unicode and any other encoding known by the Unicode library.
      I have chosen the <ulink url="http://icu-project.org/">International Components for Unicode</ulink>
      library as it provides strong cross-platform Unicode support with built-in regular expressions.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="discussion">
    <title>Dicussion, Mailing Lists, Bug Reports, etc...</title>
    <para>
      All public discussion, feature requests, bug reports, and talk of related technologies happen in
      the <ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/constraint-grammar">Constraint Grammar via Google Groups</ulink>.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
