<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "docbook-dtd-45/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="tags">
  <title>Tags</title>

  <para>
    First some example tags as we know them from CG-2 and VISLCG:
    <screen>
    "&lt;wordform&gt;"
    "baseform"
    &lt;W-max&gt;
    ADV
    @error
    (&lt;civ&gt; N)
  </screen>
  </para>
  <para>
    Now some example tags as they may look in VISL CG-3:
    <screen>
    "&lt;Wordform&gt;"i
    "^[Bb]ase.*"r
    /^@&lt;?ADV&gt;?$/r
    &lt;W&gt;65&gt;
    (&lt;F&gt;=15&gt; &lt;F&lt;=30&gt;)
    !ADV
    ^&lt;dem&gt;
    (N &lt;civ&gt;)
  </screen>
  </para>

  <section id="tag-order">
    <title>Tag Order</title>
    <para>
      Starting with the latter, (N &lt;civ&gt;), as this merely signifies that tags
      with multiple parts do not have to match in-order; (N &lt;civ&gt;) is the same
      as (&lt;civ&gt; N). This is different from previous versions of CG, but I deemed
      it unncecessary to spend extra time checking the tag order when hash lookups can
      verify the existence so fast.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="literal-string-modifiers">
    <title>Literal String Modifiers</title>
    <para>
      The first two additions to the feature sheet all display what I refer to as
      literal string modifiers, and there are two of such: 'i' for case-insensitive,
      and 'r' for a regular expression match.
      Using these modifiers will significantly slow down the matching as a hash lookup will no
      longer be enough. You can combine 'ir' for case-insensitive regular expressions.
      Regular expressions are evaluated via ICU, so
      <ulink url="http://icu-project.org/userguide/regexp.html">their documentation</ulink> is a good source.
      Regular expressions may also contain groupings that can later be used in variable string tags (see below).
    </para>
    <para>
      Due to tags themselves needing the occasional escaping, regular expressions need double-escaping of
      symbols that have special meaning to CG-3. E.g. literal non-grouping ()
      need to be written as "a\\(b\\)c"r. Metacharacters also need double-escaping, so \w needs to be written as \\w.
    </para>
    <para>
      This will not work for wordforms used as the first qualifier of a rule, e.g:
      <screen>
        "&lt;wordform&gt;"i SELECT (tag) ;
      </screen>
      but those can be rewritten in a form such as
      <screen>
        SELECT ("&lt;wordform&gt;"i) + (tag) ;
      </screen>
      which will work, but be slightly slower.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="regex-icase">
    <title>Regular Expressions</title>
    <para>
      Tags in the form //r and //i and //ri are general purpose regular expression and case insensitive matches
      that may act on any tag type, and unlike Literal String Modifiers they can do partial matches. Thus a tag like
      /^@&lt;?ADV&gt;?$/r will match any of @&lt;ADV, @&lt;ADV&gt;, @ADV&gt;, and plain @ADV.
      A tag like /word/ri will match any tag containing a substring with any case-variation of the text 'word'.
      Asides from that, the rules and gotchas are the same as for Literal String Modifiers.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="variable-strings">
    <title>Variable Strings</title>
    <para>
      Variable string tags contain markers that are replaced with matches from the previously run grouping regular expression tag.
      Regular expression tags with no groupings will not have any effect on this behavior.
      Time also has no effect, so one could theoretically perform a group match in a previous rule and use the results later,
      though that would be highly unpredictable in practice.
    </para>
    <para>
      Variable string tags are in the form of "string"v, "&lt;string&gt;"v, and &lt;string&gt;v, where variables matching
      $1 through $9 will be replaced with the corresponding group from the regular expression match.
      Multiple occurances of a single variable is allowed, so e.g. "$1$2$1"v would contain group 1 twice.
    </para>
    <para>
      One can also manipulate the case of the resulting tag via %U, %u, %L, and %l.
      %U upper-cases the entire following string.
      %u upper-cases the following single letter.
      %L lower-cases the entire following string.
      %l lower-cases the following single letter.
      The case folding is performed right-to-left one-by-one.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is also possible to include references to unified $$sets or &amp;&amp;sets in {} where they will be replaced
      with the tags that the unification resulted in. If there are multiple tags, they will be delimited by an underscore _.
    </para>
    <para>
      It should be noted that you can use varstring tags anywhere, not just when manipulating tags.
      When used in a contextual test they are fleshed out with the information available at the time and then attempted matched.
    </para>
    <para>
      <screen>
        # Adds a lower-case &lt;wordform&gt; to all readings.
        ADD (&lt;%L$1&gt;v) TARGET ("&lt;(.*)&gt;"r) ;

        # Adds a reading with a normalized baseform for all suspicious wordforms ending in 'ies'
        APPEND ("$1y"v N P NOM) TARGET N + ("&lt;(.*)ies&gt;"r) IF (1 VFIN) ;

        # Merge results from multiple unified $$sets into a single tag
        LIST ROLE = human anim inanim (bench table) ;
        LIST OTHER = crispy waffles butter ;
        MAP (&lt;{$$ROLE}/{$$OTHER}&gt;v) (target tags) (-1 $$OTHER) (-2C $$ROLE) ;
      </screen>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="numerical-matches">
    <title>Numerical Matches</title>
    <para>
      Then there are the numerical matches, e.g. &lt;W&gt;65&gt;.
      This will match tags such as &lt;W:204&gt; and &lt;W=156&gt; but not &lt;W:32&gt;.
      The second tag, (&lt;F&gt;15&gt; &lt;F&lt;30&gt;), matches values 15&gt;F&gt;30.
      These constructs are also slower than simple hash lookups.
    </para>
    <para>
      The two special values MIN and MAX (both case-sensitive) will scan the cohort for their respective minimum
      or maximum value, and use that for the comparison.
      Internally the value is stored in a double, and the range is capped between -281474976710656.0 to +281474976710655.0,
      and using values beyond that range will also act as those limits.
      <screen>
        # Select the maximum value of W. Readings with no W will also be removed.
        SELECT (&lt;W=MAX&gt;) ;

        # Remove the minimum F. Readings with no F will not be removed.
        REMOVE (&lt;N=MIN&gt;) ;
      </screen>
    </para>
    <para>
      <table id="numeric-operators">
        <title>Valid Operators</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Operator</entry>
              <entry>Meaning</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>=</entry>
              <entry>Equal to</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>!=</entry>
              <entry>Not equal to</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&lt;</entry>
              <entry>Less than</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&gt;</entry>
              <entry>Greater than</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&lt;=</entry>
              <entry>Less than or equal to</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&gt;=</entry>
              <entry>Greater than or equal to</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>&lt;&gt;</entry>
              <entry>Not equal to</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      Anywhere that an = is valid you can also use : for backwards compatibility.
    </para>
    <para>
      <table id="numeric-truths">
        <title>Comparison Truth Table</title>
        <tgroup cols="3">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>A</entry>
              <entry>B</entry>
              <entry>Result</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>= x</entry>
            <entry>= y</entry>
            <entry>True if x = y</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>= x</entry>
            <entry>!= y</entry>
            <entry>True if x != y</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>= x</entry>
            <entry>&lt; y</entry>
            <entry>True if x &lt; y</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>= x</entry>
            <entry>&gt; y</entry>
            <entry>True if x &gt; y</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>= x</entry>
            <entry>&lt;= y</entry>
            <entry>True if x &lt;= y</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>= x</entry>
            <entry>&gt;= y</entry>
            <entry>True if x &gt;= y</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>&lt; x</entry>
            <entry>!= y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&lt; x</entry>
            <entry>&lt; y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&lt; x</entry>
            <entry>&gt; y</entry>
            <entry>True if x &gt; y</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&lt; x</entry>
            <entry>&lt;= y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&lt; x</entry>
            <entry>&gt;= y</entry>
            <entry>True if x &gt; y</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>&gt; x</entry>
            <entry>!= y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&gt; x</entry>
            <entry>&gt; y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&gt; x</entry>
            <entry>&lt;= y</entry>
            <entry>True if x &lt; y</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&gt; x</entry>
            <entry>&gt;= y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>&lt;= x</entry>
            <entry>!= y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&lt;= x</entry>
            <entry>&lt;= y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&lt;= x</entry>
            <entry>&gt;= y</entry>
            <entry>True if x &gt;= y</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>&gt;= x</entry>
            <entry>!= y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>&gt;= x</entry>
            <entry>&gt;= y</entry>
            <entry>Always true</entry>
          </row>

          <row>
            <entry>!= x</entry>
            <entry>!= y</entry>
            <entry>True if x = y</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="stream-metadata">
    <title>Stream Metadata</title>
    <para>
      CG-3 will <link linkend="streamformats">store and forward</link> any data between cohorts,
      attached to the preceding cohort.
      <code>META:/.../r</code> and <code>META:/.../ri</code> lets you query and capture from this data with regular expressions.
      Data before the first cohort is not accessible.
    </para>
    <screen>
      ADD (@header) (*) IF (-1 (META:/&lt;h\d+&gt;$/ri)) ;
    </screen>
    <para>
      I recommend keeping META tags in the contextual tests, since they cannot currently be cached and will be checked
      every time.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="stream-static-tags">
    <title>Stream Static Tags</title>
    <para>
      In the CG and Apertium stream formats, it is allowed to have tags after the word form / surface form.
      These tags behave as if they contextually exist in every reading of the cohort - they will not be seen by rule targets.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="global-variables">
    <title>Global Variables</title>
    <para>
      Global variables are manipulated with rule types <link linkend="setvariable">SETVARIABLE</link> and
      <link linkend="remvariable">REMVARIABLE</link>, plus the stream commands <link linkend="cmd-setvar">SETVAR</link>
      and <link linkend="cmd-remvar">REMVAR</link>.
      Global variables persist until unset and are not bound to any window, cohort, or reading.
    </para>
    <para>
      You can query a global variable with the form VAR:name (implemented) or query whether a variable has a
      specific value with VAR:name=value (not implemented just yet).
    </para>
    <screen>
      REMOVE (@poetry) IF (0 (VAR:news)) ;
      SELECT (&lt;historical&gt;) IF (0 (VAR:year=1764)) ;
    </screen>
    <para>
      I recommend keeping VAR tags in the contextual tests, since they cannot currently be cached and will be checked
      every time.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="fail-fast-tag">
    <title>Fail-Fast Tag</title>
    <para>
      A Fail-Fast tag is the ^ prefix, such as ^&lt;dem&gt;.
      This will be checked first of a set and if found will block the set from matching,
      regardless of whether later independent tags could match.
      It is mostly useful for sets such as LIST SetWithFail = (N &lt;bib&gt;) (V TR) ^&lt;dem&gt;.
      This set will never match a reading with a &lt;dem&gt; tag, even if the reading matches (V TR).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="strict-tags">
    <title>STRICT-TAGS</title>
    <para>
      If you are worried about typos or need to otherwise enforce a strict tagset, <code>STRICT-TAGS</code> is your friend.
      You can add tags to the list of allowed tags with <code>STRICT-TAGS += ... ;</code> where <code>...</code> is a list
      of tags to allow. Any tag parsed while the STRICT-TAGS list is non-empty will be checked against the list, and an
      error will be thrown if the tag is not on the list.
    </para>
    <para>
      It is currently only possible to add to the list, hence <code>+=</code>.
      Removing and assigning can be added if anyone needs those.
    </para>
    <screen>
      STRICT-TAGS += N V ADJ etc ... ;
    </screen>
    <para>
      By default, STRICT-TAGS always allows wordforms, baseforms, regular expressions, case-insensitive, and VISL-style secondary tags
      (<code>"&lt;…&gt;"</code>, <code>"…"</code>, <code>&lt;…&gt;</code>), since those are too prolific to list
      individually. If you are extra paranoid, you can change that with <link linkend="grammar-options">OPTIONS</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      To get a list of unique used tags, pass --show-tags to CG-3. To filter this list to the default set of interesting tags,
      <link linkend="cg-strictify">cg-strictify</link> can be used:
      <screen>
        cg-strictify grammar-goes-here
      </screen>
      <emphasis>For comparison, this yields 285 tags for VISL's 10000-rule Danish grammar.</emphasis>
      Edit the resulting list to remove any tags you can see are typos or should otherwise not be allowed,
      stuff it at the top of the grammar, and recompile the grammar.
      Any errors you get will be lines where forbidden tags are used, which can be whole sets if those sets aren't used in any rules.
    </para>
    <para>
      Once you have a suitable STRICT-TAGS list, you can further trim the grammar by taking advantage the fact that any
      tag listed in STRICT-TAGS may be used as an implicit set that contains only the tag itself.
      No more need for <code>LIST N = N ;</code> constructs.
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
